Wash your hands and introduce yourself confirming the patient's identity.
Prepare the otoscope in front of the patient.
Confirm the light is bright and use a large speculum for an adult and a smaller one for a child.
While doing this explain the procedure gaining consent to examine the ears.
With the patient seated, ask if they have ear symptoms and inspect the more normal one first.
Pay attention to the pina and behind the mastoid are you looking for any redness and swelling.
Note scars, pits, sinuses, fistually, broken skin or pus in and around the tragus and pre-urricular
areas.
Before autoscopy, wipe away any pus and gently palpate the tragus for tenderness.
Ask about pain and observe the patient for any wincing.
When examining the right ear, use your right hand holding the arc light like
a pen, steadying
your hand on the cheek.
As the ear canal is curved, pull the pinna upwards and backwards to straighten it.
And children pull straight back.
Place a speculum tip by the opening of the ear canal, then bring your
eye in close to
view the external matus and the canal.
You are likely to see hairs and wax, note any foreign bodies or redness.
Remind the patient you are going to advance the tip of the speculum further
into the canal.
to speculate gently and slowly forwards and upwards in the direction of the eye.
Do this
until you can see the tympanic membrane.
If you cannot see the membrane, reposition, remembering
to point towards the eye.
If there is still no view, then the canal may be stenosed or
an ear washout may be needed to remove wax or pus.
If it is too painful, then stop.
Once you see the membrane, examine in a circular motion following the annulus, taking note
of the main features.
These can include the cone of light, umbil, pars flaccida, lateral process of malleus,
incus, handle of malleus and pars tensor.
Signs of disease may include scarring of
the membrane, redness and new vessels, pus,
sucking in of the membrane and any perforations, both small and large.
After the examination, thank the patient, explain your findings and finish by washing your hands
and the speculum.